A Finding Aid to the Helen DeMott Papers, 1896-1997, in the Archives of American Art AAA.demohele
Archives of American Art
Helen DeMott papers
1896-1997
AAA.demohele
Archives of American Art
7.9 Linear feet
The papers of painter Helen DeMott measure 7.9 linear feet and date from 1896-1997. DeMott's painting career from 1940-1996 is documented through her numerous sketchbooks and original artwork. Also found is biographical material, correspondence, writings and poems, scrapbooks, printed material, photographic material, audio and video recordings, and scattered material from collagist Ray Johnson.
DeMott, Helen, 1920-1997
Provenance
The Helen DeMott papers were a bequest to the Archives of American Art in 2003 by James Goldiner, executive for the estate of Helen DeMott.
Alternative Forms Available
Videotapes in the collection were digitized in September 2009 and are available upon request from the Archives of American Art.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Helen DeMott (1920-1997) was a New York City based painter and poet and well-known East Village community activist.
In the 1940s, DeMott attended the National Academy of Design and Art Students League. In the late 1960s, DeMott began focusing her work on the scientific study of waves, specifically the structure of water wave surfaces, a theme that remained in her work for the rest of her career. In 1974-1975, DeMott completed two building murals of water wave structures in New York City: Wave Spill, located at 155 First Avenue and 10th Street; and River Wave, at 509 Amsterdam Avenue. She had a solo exhibition at the Green Mountain Gallery in 1969, and exhibited at the ground-breaking alternative space, 112 Workshop/112 Greene Street in 1979. DeMott was received a number of grants and awards throughout her career including National Community Arts Competition winner in 1974, a grant from the New York State Council on the Arts (CAPS) in 1976, a National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship in 1978, and a Gottleib Foundation grant in 1983. She passed away in 1997.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter Helen DeMott measure 7.9 linear feet and date from 1896-1997. DeMott's painting career from 1940-1996 is documented through her numerous sketchbooks and original artwork. Also found is biographical material, correspondence, writings and poems, scrapbooks, printed material, photographic material, audio and video recordings, and scattered material from collagist Ray Johnson.
The scattered biographical material contains official documents, DeMott's resume, circulars and receipts from the Art School of the National Academy of Design, and two obituaries. Correspondence includes letters from publishers regarding DeMott's book proposal "Geography into Landscape," correspondence with universities and scientific institutions regarding her Wave series, and personal correspondence including letters from photographer, filmmaker, and painter Rudy Burckhardt, writer Alfred Chester, painter Clifford Wright, and collagist Edith Schloss.
The bulk of the writings is DeMott's poetry, as well as some artist's statements, loose notes, a speech, travel diaries, and handwritten, typed, and edited manuscripts, including a typed manuscript of "Geography into Landscape." Writings by others include poetry by Celia Bland, Miriam Finkelstein, and Marie Ponsot. Scrapbooks document DeMott's research and artwork related to waves and includes clippings, photographs of artwork, sketches and notations, and typed notes on painting waves. Printed material includes magazine and newspaper articles about Helen DeMott and various other artists, and many articles related to water waves.
Photographic material includes black and white photographs of DeMott's artwork and personal photographs. Of interest is a 1943 photograph of a group at the Art Students League which includes Ester Rolick, Edith Schloss, Max Eastman, and Helen DeMott. Also found are slides and transparencies of artwork and slides for lectures on waves. Audiovisual Recordings include one reel-to-reel tape and five videotapes, some related to DeMott's study of waves.
There is one folder of material from collagist Ray Johnson containing scattered letters and mail art, exhibition fliers, and collages. Measuring 4.2 linear feet, the bulk of DeMott's papers are sketchbooks and original artwork spanning her artistic career. There are numerous loose sketches, notes, sketchbooks, holiday cards, watercolors, and oversized drawings in pencil, ink, and oil pastels, much of which is related to waves. Original artwork by others includes Esther Rolick and Edith Schloss.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1911-1997 (Boxes 1, 9; 7 folders)
Series 2: Letters and Correspondence, 1896, 1930-1995 (Boxes 1-2; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1950-circa 1996 (Boxes 2-3; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1967-1989 (Box 3; 2 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1961-1996 (Boxes 3, 9; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographic Material, circa 1920s-1996 (Boxes 3-4, 9; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Audiovisual Recordings, 1975, 1978, undated (Box 4; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 8: Ray Johnson, 1947, 1963, undated (Box 4; 1 folder)
Series 9: Artwork, 1941-1996 (Boxes 4-9, OV 10-13; 4.2 linear feet)
Art Students League (New York, N.Y.). -- Photographs; Bland, Celia; Burkhardt, Rudy; Chester, Alfred, 1928-1971; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969; Finkelstein, Miriam; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Ponsot, Marie; Rolick, Esther G., b. 1922; Schloss, Edith, 1919-; Wright, Clifford, 1919-; Drawings; Manuscripts; Notes; Photographs; Poems; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; Travel diaries; Video recordings; Watercolors; Women artists
- Biographical Material, 1911-1997; Series 1; 7 Folders Boxes 1, 9
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material contains official documents, DeMott's resume, circulars and receipts from the Art School of the National Academy of Design, and two obituaries.
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Birth Certificate, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diploma, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 1.
  - Marriage Certificate, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - National Academy of Design, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Obituary, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Blessed Sacrament Academy Diploma, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 1, Folder 3.
- Letters and Correspondence, 1896, 1930-1995; Series 2; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Both business and personal correspondence are found in this series. Business correspondence includes correspondence with publishers regarding DeMott's book proposal "Geography into Landscape," with universities and scientific institutions regarding the Wave series, with galleries, museums, art programs and foundations, and correspondence regarding her various committee and community activities. Much of the personal correspondence is from friends living or traveling outside of the United States; many address DeMott with familiarity and fondness, using the salutation, "Ho!" Among the correspondents are photographer, filmmaker, and painter Rudy Burckhardt, writer Alfred Chester, painter Clifford Wright, and collagist Edith Schloss. There is also a large quantity of personal postcards.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of correspondence, then by subject. Undated correspondence is filed at the back of each folder.
  - Business, 1934-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
  - Business, Book Proposal: Geography into Landscape, circa 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Business, Ottendorf Library, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal, 1896, 1930-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-19)
  - Personal, Burckhardt, Rudy, 1947-1952, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Personal, Chester, Alfred, 1960-1965, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Personal, DeMott, Helen, 1987-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Personal, Hacker, Lucia Vernarelli, 1947-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Personal, Schloss, Edith, 1947-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - Personal, Wright, Clifford, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Postcards, 1943-1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Postcards, 1953-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Writings, 1950-circa 1996; Series 3; 1 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  The bulk of the material found in this series is poetry written by DeMott in notebooks and on loose paper. Also found are artist's statements, loose notes, a speech, travel diaries, and handwritten, typed, and edited manuscripts, including a typed manuscript of "Geography into Landscape." Writings by others includes music scores and essays, but the bulk of the material is poetry by Celia Bland, Miriam Finkelstein, Marie Ponsot, and others.
  Writings by Helen DeMott are filed before writings by others. Folders are then arranged alphabetically by subject or title.
  - Writings by Helen DeMott (Box 2)
    - Artist's Statements, 1981, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Contains original artwork.
    - "Cezanne's 'The Cardplayers'.....What's in a Game?", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "The Chronicle of Sonta Kerosina", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - City Planning Commmission Speech, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Geography into Landscape", circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "How 'Ho' Became the Battle-Cry of Chelsea,", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Lone Dog's Winter Count", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Mother Goose Cookbook", 1964, 1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Notebooks, Loose Notes, 1964-1996, undated (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
    - Notebooks, Poetry, 1989-1996 (Box 2, Folder 16-21)
    - Notes, Various, 1968, 1983, 1991-1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Notes, Waves, 1974-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Octopus in the Metropolis", 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Poetry, DeMott, Helen, 1952, 1989-1996 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Travel Diary: France, Italy, Greece and Turkey, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Waves, circa 1970s, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Writings by Others (Box 3)
    - Allan, Sergio Borges, "The Indian Space Painters,", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Goldscheider, Ludwig, "Jan Vermeer: The Paintings Complete Edition,", undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Music Tablature, 1968-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Poetry, Bland, Celia, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Poetry, Finkelstein, Miriam, 1990-1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Poetry, Ponsot, Marie, 1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Poetry, Various Artists, A-Z, 1994-1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Scrapbooks, 1967-1989; Series 4; 2 Folders Box 3
  Scrapbooks related to DeMott's Waves series includes clippings, photographs of artwork, sketches and notations, and typed notes on painting waves. Much of the material is photocopied.
  Folders are arranged chronologically.
  - Waves, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Waves, 1967-1975, 1985-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Printed Material, 1961-1996; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 3, 9
  Printed material includes magazine and newspaper articles about DeMott, various other artists, and scientific articles related to water waves. Also found are clippings of images, exhibition announcements, a sign, and a poster. Many articles are photocopies.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Catalogue, "Artists of the Lower East Side,", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1977-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Sign, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1969-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, Various Artists, 1982-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Magazine Clippings, Bore and Meander, Chaos (Fractals), 1979-1996 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Magazine Clippings, Helen DeMott, 1963-1977, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Poster, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 2.
  - Various Printed Material, Clippings of Images, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Various Printed Material, New York City Housing, 1961-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Conch Music" Poster, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 17.
- Photographic Material, circa 1920s-1996; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 9
  Photographic material includes black and white photographs of DeMott's artwork and personal photographs. Most of the artwork photographs are taken by Rudulph (Rudy) Burckhardt and have notations on the back with dimensions, title, date of creation, and ownership information. Personal photographs are mostly snapshots of unidentified persons in New York and Italy, circa 1920s-1930s, and DeMott and others with dogs, circa 1960s-1990s. Also found are slides of artwork, slides for lectures on waves, notes on slides, and transparencies of artwork.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of material, then by subject.
  - Photographs and Negatives (Box 3)
    - Artwork (1940-1982), undated (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
    - Ocean Photographs, 1967, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 3.
    - Personal, circa 1920s-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 24-30)
      Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 4.
  - Slides (Box 3)
    - Artwork (1945-1991), undated (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
  - Slides (Box 4)
    - Artwork, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Artwork by Cezanne and Caravaggio, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Lectures Slides (Waves), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notes on Slides, 1978-1996, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Personal (1971-1982), undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Transparencies, Artwork, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ocean Photographs, 1967, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Oversized photographs from Box 3, Folder 23.
  - Personal, "Fun for Funds," Art Students League, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Oversized photograph from Box 3, Folders 24-30.
- Audiovisual Recordings, 1975, 1978, undated; Series 7; 0.4 Linear feet Box 4
  Found is one sound tape reel (1/4 in. tape) of a music recording and two video recordings on five videoreels (1/2 in. tape), including "Chorda," a dance performance, and multiple copies of DeMott's "Wave Notes."
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of material, then by title.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  All of the video recordings have been digitized for research access.
  - Bach, Suite #3, undated; 1 sound tape reels (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Chorda", 1978 March 31; 1 Videoreels (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Wave Notes", 1975 July 17; 4 Videoreels (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    Original videoreel and three duplicate videoreels.
- Ray Johnson, 1947, 1963, undated; Series 8; 1 Folders Box 4
  Found is one folder of scattered letters, mail art, exhibition fliers, and collages by collagist Ray Johnson.
  - Collages/Mail Art/Letters, 1947, 1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Artwork, 1941-1996; Series 9; 4.2 Linear feet Boxes 4-9, OV 10-13
  The bulk of the material found are sketchbooks from 1941-1996 and DeMott's original artwork related to water waves. The sketchbooks primarily contain pencil and ink drawings; many also include notes on and sketches of waves. Also found are numerous loose sketches and notes, holiday cards, watercolors, and oversized drawings in pencil, ink, and oil pastels. Original artwork by others include Esther Rolick and Edith Schloss.
  - Drawings, 1941-1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folders 6-9 and OV 13.
  - Drawings, European Landscapes, circa 1950s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folders 10-11.
  - Drawings and Printed Material (used for reference), 1979-1996, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Gifts of Artwork to Helen DeMott, 1941-1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 12.
  - Holiday Cards, Miscellaneous, 1964-1971, 1985-1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Pastel on Paper, 1961-1966 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 13.
  - Pastel on Paper, 1966-1990, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 14, and OV 13.
  - Postcard Collages by Others, 1948, 1969, 1981-1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Prints, 1942-1948, 1963-1968, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbooks, 1941-1975 (Box 5, Folder 4-19)
  - Sketchbooks, 1976-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
  - Sketchbooks, 1986-1996, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
  - Watercolors, 1942-1966, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Oversized material housed in OV 13.
  - Wave Series, 1967-1971 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Wave Series, 1971-1996, undated (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, Folder 15, and OV 10-12.
  - Oversized Collage Poster, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Drawings, 1959-circa 1966 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folders 12-14.
  - Oversized Drawings, 1976-1980 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Drawings, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Drawings, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Drawings, European Landscapes, circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 15.
  - Oversized Gifts of Artwork to Helen DeMott, 1959-1969 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 17.
  - Oversized Pastel on Paper, 1962-1964 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 19.
  - Oversized Pastel on Paper, 1982-1990 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Oversized material from Box 5, Folder 1.
  - Oversized Wave Series, 1980-1996, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Oversized material from Box 8, Folders 1-3.
  - Oversized Wave Series, 1978, 1986-1991 (Box OV 10)
  - Oversized Wave Series, 1992-1993 (Box OV 11)
  - Oversized Wave Series, 1993-1996, undated (Box OV 12)
  - Oversized Drawings, 1943 (Box OV 13)
  - Oversized Pastel on Paper, 1990 (Box OV 13)
  - Oversized Watercolors, 1958, 1965-1966 (Box OV 13)
    Oversized material from Box 7, Folder 10.